picture this a machine that could
organize your cupboard just as you like
it or serve every member of the house a
customized cup of coffee makes your day
easier doesn't it these are the products
of artificial intelligence but why use
the term artificial intelligence
well these machines are artificially
incorporated with human-like
intelligence to perform tasks as we do
this intelligence is built using complex
algorithms and mathematical functions
but AI may not be as obvious as in the
previous examples in fact AI is used in
smartphones cars social media feeds
video games banking surveillance and
many other aspects of our daily life the
real question is what does an AI do at
its core here is a robot we built in our
lab which is now dropped onto a field in
spite of a variation in lighting
landscape and dimensions of the field
the AI robot must perform as expected
this ability to react appropriately to a
new situation is called generalized
learning the robot is now at a crossroad
one that is paved in the other rocky the
robot must determine which path to take
based on the circumstances this portrays
the robots reasoning ability after a
short stroll the robot now encounters a
stream that it cannot swim across using
the plank provided as an input the robot
is able to cross this stream so our
robot uses the given input and finds the
solution for a problem this is problem
solving these three capabilities make
the robot artificially intelligent in
short AI provides machines with the
capability to adapt reason and provide
solutions well now that we know what a
is let's have a look at the two broad
categories in AI is classified into weak
AI also called narrow AI focuses solely
on one task for example alphago is a
maestro of the game go but you can't
expect it to be even remotely good at
this makes alphago a weak AI you might
say Alexa is definitely not a weak AI
since it can perform multiple tasks well
that's not really true when you ask
Alexa to play this besito it picks up
the key words play and dispose IDO and
runs a program and is trained - Alexa
cannot respond to a question it isn't
trained to answer for instance try
asking Alexa the status of traffic from
work to home
Alexa cannot provide you this
information as she is not trained - and
that brings us to our second category of
AI strong AI now this is much like the
robots that only exist in fiction as of
now
Ultron from Avengers is an ideal example
of a strong AI that's because it's
self-aware and eventually even develops
emotions
this makes the a eyes response
unpredictable you must be wondering well
how is artificial intelligence different
from machine learning and deep learning
we saw what a is machine learning is a
technique to achieve AI and deep
learning in turn is a subset of machine
learning machine learning provides a
machine with the capability to learn
from data and experience throughout
rhythms deep learning does this learning
through ways inspired by the human brain
this means through deep learning data
and patterns can be better perceived Ray
Kurzweil a well known futurist
predicts that by the Year 2045 we would
have robots as smart as humans this is
called the point of singularity well
that's not all in fact Elon Musk
predicts that the human mind and body
will be enhanced by AI implants which
would make us partly cyborgs so here's a
question for you which of the below AI
projects don't exist yet a an AI robot
with citizenship be a robot with a
muscular skeletal system see a AI that
can read its owner's emotions
the AI that develops emotions over time
give it a thought and leave your answers
in the comments section below three
lucky winners will receive Amazon gift
vouchers since the human brain is still
a mystery it's no surprise that AI 2 has
a lot of unvented domains for now
AI is built to work with humans and make
our tasks easier however with the
maturation of technology we can only
wait and watch what the future of AI
holds for us
well that is artificial intelligence for
you in short do not forget to leave your
answer to the quiz in the comment
section below also like share and
subscribe to our channel if you enjoyed
this video stay tuned and keep learning
[Music]
you