The Internet of Things or iot
is influencing our lifestyle
from the way we react
to the way we behave.
From air conditioners
that you can control
with your smartphone
to Smart Cars providing
the shortest route
or your Smartwatch
which is tracking
your daily activities.
IoT is a giant network
with connected devices.
These devices gather
and share data about
how they are used
and the environment
in which they are operated.
It's all done using sensors,
sensors are embedded
in every physical device.
It can be your mobile
phone, electrical appliances
Pecos barcode sensors
traffic lights and almost
everything that you come across
in day-to-day life. These sensors
continuously emit data
about the working state
of the devices,
but the important question is
how do they share
this huge amount of data,
And how do we put this data
to our benefit iot
provides a common platform
for all these devices
to dump their data.
And a Common language
for all the devices to
communicate with each other. Data
is emitted from various sensors
and sent to iot
platform security iot platform
integrates the collected data
from various sources
further analytics is
performed on the data
and valuable information
is extracted as per requirement.
Finally.
The result is shared
with other devices for better
user experience Automation
and improving efficiencies.
Let us look at a scenario
where iot is doing wonders.
In an AC manufacturing industry
both the manufacturing machine
and the Belt have
sensors attached they
continuously send data
regarding the machine health
and the production specifics
to the manufacturer
to identify issues beforehand.
A barcode is attached
to each product
before leaving the belt.
It contains the product
code, manufacturer details,
special instructions Etc.
The manufacturer uses
this data to identify
where the product
was distributed and track
the Retailer's inventory hence,
the manufacturer can make
the product running
out of stock available
Next this products
are packed and parcel
to different retailers.
Each retailer has
a barcode reader to track
the products coming
from different manufacturers,
manage inventory, check
special instructions
and many more. The compressor
of air conditioner
has an embedded sensor
that emits data regarding
its health and temperature.
This data is not allies
continuously allowing
the customer care to contact you
for the repair work in time.
This is just one
of the million scenarios.
We have Smart appliances, Smart
Cars, Smart Homes, smart Cities
where iot is redefining
our lifestyle and transforming
the way we interact
with Technologies.
The future of iot industry is
huge. Business Insider
intelligence estimates
that 24 billion iot devices
will be installed by 2020
and ITC predicts
that iot Revenue will reach
around three hundred
and fifty seven billion
in 2019 resulting in a lot
of job opportunities
in the IT industry.
Want to become a part
of the iot Revolution, come
and master iot with Edureka.