[Music]
what's up guys welcome to another video
brought to you by the simple engineer in
today's video we are going to dive into
docker and containers let's get right
into it so years ago before containers
were a thing we had big companies like
Walmart Target Chase Bank you name it
and they needed to make sure that their
business never went down because their
business was technology they relied on
it so what they would do is they would
go buy servers and then they would go
buy more servers and then that process
would rinse and repeat and they
basically would over allocate more than
they needed and the issue is that with
this was it was extremely extremely
expensive and they needed to do this
because as more and more users hit their
servers they wanted to make sure that
they could scale well and in the process
that they wouldn't be able to scale well
then their servers would basically crash
and burn and their business would be
dead so fast-forward a few years we have
a really cool company it comes out and
their name is VMware and VMware says we
have this thing to offer it's known as
virtualization and what you're going to
be able to do is instead of running your
application every time you want to run
your application you go buy a new server
that's really expensive we're gonna
allow you to run multiple operating
systems on the same host which
essentially means you can run your app
in isolation on the same server the same
infrastructure but the apps aren't gonna
know anything about each other so it's
like running an entirely separate
computer on the same computer and this
was a mind-blowing thing that was a
game-changer for the industry another
point this was this was a lot more
efficient because we could actually take
advantage of the resources that we had
purchased that were so expensive because
we could run more applications in
isolation within that bare metal server
environment this was really cool because
no like I had reiterated we're running
multiple apps at once but on the same
server and before if you wanted to make
sure that you didn't really have a
single point of failure for your
application you would place them on
different servers and then scale
horizontally in that fashion
unfortunately it's not all roses and
because virtualization is expensive to
begin we have multiple kernels for every
guest operating system that is going to
be running on the infrastructure it's
going to have a kernel inside of it and
in addition to that for every guest
operating system that we add into the
infrastructure we have to allocate
resources for it although we don't have
physical hardware we have virtual
hardware so those take up resources we
have guest operating system space we
have the RAM allocation that we have for
this operating system so it's just a lot
more expensive although we do get a lot
of benefits it's still not the best
thing out there so fast forward to
modern-day containerization we have a
fantastic technology it's known as
docker now docker is really great
because for one it's extremely
lightweight we don't have the issues of
having these crazy to configure virtual
machine images that are hard to set up
and hard to deploy docker is they work
off images and you can create containers
out of these images and it makes it
really really lightweight in addition to
that it's really portable you have these
images that are already really really
small basically these bare bone
distributions and you can use
configuration like docker files to
basically spin these things up
instantaneously on pretty much any
system next it is extremely extremely
fast before you'd have to boot up an
entire operating system just to get to
your application and then you'd have to
copy over all of the files which could
be a tedious process docker has all of
this stuff embedded in its configuration
management it starts up within seconds
and it's really really quick to use
right there in your host machine and one
of the biggest benefits that we see from
docker that sets it apart from something
like a virtual machine is there is no
hypervisor and we'll look at that in
more detail in a second but essentially
what that means is it doesn't have a
separate kernel it is still utilizing
the same resources as the host OS and it
basically exploits namespaces and
control groups too tightly use these
resources in a more
efficient way so now let us actually
compare and contrast virtualization
versus containerization when we're
looking at virtualization from a diagram
type view we know that it has
infrastructure infrastructure is going
to represent what your server is the
bare metal the host it could be your
laptop your desktop a high-end server
what-have-you on top of that we have the
operating system and the operating
system is going to be something like
Windows Server could be even your
personal laptop like Mac OS or some
Linux distribution
in virtualization we have something
known as a hypervisor and because we're
running these virtual machines which are
basically isolated desktop environments
inside of a file the hypervisor is
what's going to understand how to read
that file and this is what a virtual
machine images and common hypervisors
are things like VMware and VirtualBox
and they know how to interpret these
operating systems and then on top of
that we have the actual guest OS and
each one of these guest OS is has their
own kernel and this is where things
start to get a little bit expensive from
a resource allocation perspective and
then on top of the OS is where we would
actually install our binaries and our
libraries and then finally we could copy
over all of our files on to this
operating system that actually makes up
our application that we want to deploy
on the server now let's contrast this to
containerization containerization has
infrastructure of course things like
what we had just mentioned and in
addition to that it has the operating
system but what's different is it
doesn't actually have a hypervisor it
has a process that runs directly on the
operating system known as the docker
Damon and the docker daemon is what
facilitates and manages things like the
running containers on the system the
images that you create and all of the
command line utilities that come with
docker
the applications that we run within
these images basically run directly on
the exact host machine and what happens
is we create images which are like
copies of the application that we want
to distribute and a running instance of
an image is
what's known as a container and each
container has one process in a typically
our application what it does is it
actually segments utilizing things like
name spacing and control groups to
piggyback off the resources directly on
the host machine so we're using the same
kernel but we're using namespaces to say
hey this is the segment of the system
that you can have and control groups
will say this is how much of that thing
that you can have this is how much RAM
you can have this is how much network
bandwidth you are allocated and that is
how docker exploits the operating system
that it runs on without needing a
hypervisor so it's really beneficial
because we are on the same host we can
more tightly couple ourselves to the
resources of the operating system and
the system that we're running on and on
top of all of that it's just a lot
faster and it's a lot more portable so
that's why a lot of people are
preferring docker over the traditional
virtual machine I want to touch on just
a few more points and the main one is we
fix the problem using docker when people
say it works on my computer but not
theirs
this problem goes away and this is
because we packaged a working running
instance of our application inside of an
image and then that's the thing that
gets deployed so there's never any of
this hey it works on my machine but it
doesn't work on their machine docker
resolves that issue in addition to this
we have better dependency management
typically you have your dependencies
scattered all across your application
and then deploying it on another server
is a very time-consuming tedious process
but within docker we bake all of our
dependencies into the image directly so
it makes it a lot easier to manage all
of those dependencies and then of course
the main thing that we've reiterated in
multiple times in this video is it is a
lot more lightweight than something like
a typical virtual machine and that's a
huge benefit when trying to quickly or
Zonta lea and vertically scale your
applications and that does it for this
video stay tuned for the rest of the
videos in this series and don't forget
to like comment and subscribe thanks