hey what's going on everybody it's your
bro hope you're doing well and in this
video i'm going to teach you guys about
polymorphism in java so
sit back relax and enjoy the show
if you find this video helpful please
remember to like
comment and subscribe your support will
help keep this channel running
polymorphism this is a greek word for
poly meaning many
and morph meaning form or forms it's the
ability of an object to identify
as more than one type think of it as
being identified as more than one
data type here's an example let's say
we're going to have a race
and we can enter in all different sorts
of vehicles into this race they don't
all have to be the same
so we have a few additional classes a
class called vehicle
vehicle is going to act as the parent
class for my class car
so car extends vehicle bicycle bicycle
extends vehicle
and boat boat extends vehicle so car
bicycle and boat are all subclasses or
children classes of the vehicle
superclass
so let's create an instance of our car
bicycle and
boat luckily through the magic of
copying and pasting i have done that
already we have a car object
a bicycle object and a boat object so
let's store
well at least attempt to store all of
these objects within an array called
racers
bracers equals and then we will place
our car
bicycle and boat within this array so
what's the data type of this array going
to be
well we're going to have a problem could
we make this cars
well we can store our car object within
an array of cars but not our bicycle and
our boat
the same thing goes for bicycle we can
store our bicycle but not the car in the
boat
and lastly with the boat data type we
can store the boat but not the car and
the bicycle
and to solve this issue we can use the
power of polymorphism
so for example our car identifies as a
car
but since it extends the vehicle class
it also identifies as a vehicle
same thing goes with our bicycle and our
boat so
one thing they all have in common is
that they are all vehicles
so we can change the data type of this
array to vehicles
and therefore we can store our car our
bicycle
and our boat because all of these
objects also
identify as vehicles so if you're going
to store objects within an array
and they're all different object types
you would have to find what they have in
common
and make an array of that type so that's
how to store
different objects within an array using
polymorphism and now for our wrists
we're going to call
a go method that we're going to define
within each of our classes car
bicycle and boat so let's begin with car
let's create a go method
so let's make this public void it's not
returning anything
and this will be called go so when we
call this method
all we'll do is have a print line
statement system.out.printline
let's say something like the car begins
moving okay let's repeat the process for
bicycle and boat
let's change car to bicycle
and within the boat class car to boat
so each of these methods well each of
these classes
has their own go method and we could
call them individually kind of like this
car.go bicycle.go
and boat.go
so this would work but there's actually
a better way to write this
and what would be better is if we were
to create an enhanced for loop to
iterate through all of the elements of
this array of vehicles
so the data type for this enhanced for
loop is going to be vehicle
we'll use x as our counter colon and
then the name of the array which is
racers so this is going to iterate once
through all of the elements of this
array of vehicles called racers
x represents the vehicle we are
currently working with
so x dot and we would like to use the go
method
so our enhanced for loop doesn't care
what kind of vehicle you are
if you're a car a bicycle or a boat it
cares
that you're a vehicle and if you're a
vehicle use your go method whatever kind
of vehicle you are
so there's one more step to this too the
method go
is undefined for the type vehicle so we
need to make sure we have
this go method within our class of
vehicle
and i just generated that here so what
we're doing is actually
method overriding within the car the
bicycle and the bulk class
so this isn't necessary but it's
considered good practice to add the
add override annotation to each of these
methods
and then our enhanced for loop is going
to iterate through all of the elements
of our array of vehicles called
racers so it doesn't care what kind of
vehicle you are
if you're a vehicle use your go method
well luckily our car
our bicycle and our boat all also
identify as a vehicle
so that's all that polymorphism is it's
the ability of an object to identify
as more than one type think of it as
identifying as more than one data type
our car does identify as a car but it
also identifies as a vehicle
same thing can be said with our bicycle
and our boat
but not only that all objects are
children classes of the
object class so they also identify as
objects so you could write this using
the object data type but there's a few
other changes that we would have to make
so that's all that polymorphism is it's
the ability of an object to identify as
more than one type
so if you would like a copy of all this
code i will post all of this in the
comments down below
but yeah that's the basics of
polymorphism in java
hey you yeah i'm talking to you if you
learn something new
then you can help me help you in three
easy steps
by smashing that like button drop a
comment down below
and subscribe if you'd like to become a
fellow bro
[Music]
you