[Music]
welcome to master kubernetes in this
course will explore kubernetes the
leading package in one of the most
exciting and lucrative areas of
computing technology today container
orchestration and deployment will focus
on hands-on learning
but first let's explore the trends that
are given rise to containers the need
for container orchestration and how that
it's created the space for kubernetes to
rise to dominance and growth the growth
of technology into every aspect of our
lives and days has created immense
demand on software the companies and
organizations that sell and deliver
products based on software or just use
software in their businesses this really
is nearly any business and anyone who
doesn't live entirely off the grid
this pressure has spurred innovation and
standardization and the needs and stakes
are so high it is fundamentally changed
house offers developed and deployed into
production but this evolution isn't
without precedent
could you imagine the world's economy
relying on methods like this for the
trade of goods there would be no way
you'd get your new iPhone in time now we
take it for granted that shipping
containers efficiently move between
different modes of transportation
different ship owners and shipping
companies and have standardized
ubiquitous and available anywhere in the
world almost always no matter what it's
in if it fits it ships modern software
is becoming quite similar as software
systems become more complicated this
complication has driven software to be
divided into smaller pieces such as
micro services whether they're called
micro services or not these smaller
pieces of software each need to be
packaged built deployed and accessed by
other pieces of software around them to
function as a total system these small
pieces of software can be deployed into
containers that allow them to run on the
same machine virtual or real but making
it appear to the software that is the
only process running here's where we
depart from the shipping container
metaphor a bit while it should be
containers sole job is to keep things
contained within itself typically
interesting and useful software depends
on other software around it too
it's job here is where the need for
container orchestration is born there
are definite benefits and keeping
logically distinct soft fare separate
from each other you can develop deploy
scale and maintain each small piece
without too much fuss between the other
parts of the system when it's not all in
the same module however at some point
different parts of your application
likely to communicate with each other to
do something interesting for example an
API may need to communicate with
business logic it needs in turn to
access information or database
containers themselves keep logically
distinct pieces of software separate so
they can be built deployed maintained
managed and scaled on their own without
unduly affecting other parts of the
system container orchestration on the
other hand defines how these containers
interact as a system the needs between
each other and how they come together to
your performant manageable reliable and
scalable system it is currently safe to
say that docker is the dominant leader
in both technology and an adoption in
containers while others exist in the
space their dominance is so great when
you mention containers it is almost
synonymous with docker other players
exist in niche applications and some
movement around standardisation is
occurring although is nascent at the
docker file standard is essentially
today's standard and docker repositories
define the dominant way of hosting
versions of a container between
developers and between systems that need
to use them such as orchestration
systems like kubernetes since container
orchestration is a much newer space only
growing since the adoption of containers
the technologies are newer and still
evolving however kubernetes is quite
advanced and with Amazon Web Services
finally joining its competitors and
embracing kubernetes it has the backing
of nearly every major player and cloud
computing through the cloud native
computing foundation also known as the
CN CF the organization that now governs
kubernetes it has essentially
come the de facto standard especially
now that it's Mearing alternative
competing technology docker swarm
Dockers solution to container
orchestration has now announced support
for kubernetes style configuration and
processing it is clear that kubernetes
is now the de facto standard if not the
acknowledged standard in the industry
and container orchestration
containerization changed how software
was developed and packaged container
orchestration is changing how containers
are deployed into bigger useful systems
from here on out we'll focus on how to
use kubernetes as your framework for
container management using docker
containers in the next lecture we'll
focus on the growth lineage of and why
the market has chosen kubernetes