hi guys welcome back to another video by
simply learn
in this video we bring to you the top 10
iot
projects for 2020 but before we begin
if you're new here and haven't
subscribed already
make sure to hit the subscribe button
and the bell icon to never miss an
update
we come up with interesting tech videos
every day
so moving on here's the list of iot
projects
for 2020. first up is smart mirror
smart mirrors are a very cool iot
application
these mirrors can be used to display
temperature
news weather calendar clock
and complements on the screen apart from
these
smart mirrors can be used to click the
perfect selfies
with a built-in camera it can also be
installed with speakers
to play some music and they also provide
on-demand
workout sessions with world-class
trainers the mirror can be used to
browse the internet
make phone calls and even be connected
with other devices
for collaboration next up is smart money
transfer
we're heading towards complete
digitization
transactions are made possible on your
cell phone
with apps like apple pay google pay and
paypal
but imagine if you could walk to a store
and pay with the wrist watch
wouldn't that be cool the purpose of the
smart wallet is to provide an
easy and reliable platform for money
transactions
it is compact variable and rechargeable
for safety purposes the user
authenticity is validated the smart
money transfer technology
can reduce the burden of mobile money
transfer
when you're on the go you could easily
step into a store
purchase the goods and pay hassle free
after every successful transaction
the balance is updated immediately to
avoid any uncertainty
next up is iot based smart arm
now this project includes the creation
of a robotic
arm which can pick and place things from
one place to another
to control this action the robotic arm
can be moved using specific commands
some advanced arms allow the user to
change the end effect of the arm
to perform various different actions it
can be used to make
art print 3d images and build production
lines
it can also be used to perform your
day-to-day chores
at number 4 we have smart irrigation
now with change in climate and recurrent
water crisis
farmers suffer a great deal with growing
crops
smart irrigation puts an end to this
ordeal
this system comes with the moisture
sensor
that checks the soil for its water
content when the soil moisture drops
below a certain value
the system triggers the water supply at
number 5
we have smart door now as the name
suggests
this project aims at creating smart
doors
that control the entry and exit of
humans
these doors open and close automatically
when you pass by the door can also be
controlled
remotely you could unlock the door for a
friend
by tapping an icon on your smartphone
once they exit
you're immediately notified the owner
can also choose
who has the access to the door at number
we have air monitoring system now air
monitoring has become crucial for the
environment
and what better way to do it than
incorporating iot
the iot system uses air sensors to sense
the presence of
harmful gases or compounds in the air
the data collected can be used by the
local authorities
to make a detailed analysis necessary
actions can also be taken
to ensure that the air quality levels
don't reach an extreme low
especially in areas with hospitals and
schools
moving on to number seven we have smart
alarm clock
now there are many variations of a smart
but the alarm we are talking about is a
self-setting alarm
the smart alarm clock uses your google
calendar
to check your appointments to set the
alarm it can also procure
data from gps about your eta to a
particular place
and consider the weather to
automatically adjust your wake time
all of this is just making life more
easier
moving on at number eight we have iot
based
weather reporting system now the system
deals with monitoring weather
and climate changes like humidity
temperature
moisture wind speed uv radiation
light intensity and even carbon monoxide
levels in the air
using multiple sensors now these
installed sensors
send data to the web page that is
plotted as graphical statistics
the project even consists of an
application that sends notifications
as an effective alert to warn people
about
sudden and drastic weather changes so
when you're heading out
the app could easily tell you what the
weather will be like
and suggest carrying an umbrella or
perhaps a sunblock
at number nine we have smart wheelchair
there are over 132 million wheelchair
users
across the globe smart wheelchairs
is an excellent innovation typically it
comes with built-in sensors
on the seats that collect data every
second
the data provides insight into the
seating behavior of the patient
and the energy required to maintain the
posture
other variations of smart wheelchairs
could include
fall detection these features allow
people to monitor the patient from a
remote location
and finally at number 10 we have smart
street light system
this iot based street light monitoring
system
not only monitors but also ensures low
power consumption
and detects faulty lights the street
lights have external sensing
that automatically turns on at the
desired intensity
based on the lighting needed control of
light intensity
is based on the movement of people or
vehicles
in case of an emergency the lights
increase the brightness
to maximum intensity thereby ensuring
safety when deployed as a part of a
smart city
the users can be informed about any
outages
they can also register a complaint for
immediate service
so with that we come to the end of the
list
if you have any interesting projects let
us know in the comment section
so with that we end this short video on
iot projects
thank you so much for being here and
watch out for more videos from us
until then keep learning and stay tuned
to simply learn