there's a lot of buzz about
micro-services these days everybody
wants to create applications using the
micro service architecture in this video
let's look at what micro services are
really all about but rather than reading
out a like a list of architectural
concepts we will approach this from a
completely different place by me telling
you a story that you really need to know
[Music]
let's go back in time to the old days
when we didn't have anything called
microservices in fact we'll go so far
back he'll go to a time when a computer
was big enough to fill the room must
have seen pictures of one of these
things you would walk up to that
computer you would give it all the
instructions it needs to compute then it
would take it and it would execute it
all right fast forward a little bit to
desktop machines again programs resided
on the desktop machine the programmer
application contains all the
instructions that are needed to execute
so when people would write applications
for it their code would be compiled down
and the whole thing would be installed
on the computer in one go and it's been
stalled on the same computer think of
purely desktop only apps okay something
like Microsoft Word or a text editor
that you install on your machine this
has historically influenced how we write
code when we need to write an
application we would start a new code
project and we would add functionality
into that project need more
functionality add more code and so the
size of the code base for any given
application keeps increasing over time
so what starts as a small codebase might
end up turning into a large complex
codebase over time and people realize
this there were best practices that were
created to handle large projects
developers were recommended to break
things up into modules so rather than
put all your code into a single mess of
a codebase create smaller modules and
compose your application from these
modules small independent parts that
were focused on just doing a small
amount of functionality these modules
were supposed to be reusable so a simple
module could be added to another project
to help another application see isn't
this awesome and then once you've
created your application this way you're
ready to build this whole application
and deploy this on the machine that runs
your application notice something here
when coding your application you have
all these modular constructs right nice
fragmented organized pieces of
functionality pieces
code that composed together to form your
application but still what you're doing
is composing them to form one
application and when you build it and
apply it all those small pieces all get
smushed together into one giant ball of
distributable that is your final
application build and that's what you'd
apply to a machine again take the
example of your text editor installer or
Microsoft Word installer no matter how
the developers of that application have
modularized and organized their source
code the final distributable the final
executable is just one thing but
everything's mush together this is
important to remember okay remember this
picture nice fancy modularized organized
structure of the code but one
application so the final deployed entity
smushed because nobody cares how the
application looks on the user's machine
right and everything needs to be
deployed on to one machine anyway this
used to work for the most part for
desktop applications people would
happily develop and deploy applications
this way and then and then there came
along two things that would
revolutionize and maybe even associate
some changes to the way we build
applications what were those two things
first was the onset of web applications
people started to move away from
applications that needed to be installed
on the machine and towards web
applications that would be installed on
a remote server machine somewhere on the
internet and then you from your machine
can use your web browser to access the
result off that execution on the remote
machine think server-side applications
the server would prepare the HTML that
your web application needs to show and
no applications are actually deployed on
your machine but from your browser
perhaps you just use your browser the
actual application would be deployed on
the server somewhere and your requests
go to that thing and that process is it
does whatever it needs to do and then
returns back a response now you might
ask me how does this change things well
for the most part nothing much changed
initially the only change was instead of
developers installing their applications
and all the different users machines
they would install them on just one
server and all the users who just point
to that seven access that server this
was awesome right everybody gets
automatic updates very cool
but then the core and the deployment
model was still the same nice fancy
modularized organized structure of the
core but all that composes to just one
application and the final deployed
entity smushed rather than deploying the
smush on the user's machine they without
deploying that smush in one place on the
server then at some point of time due to
various different reasons some people
started wondering hmm there must be a
better way but wait let's pause the
story for a bit and let's look at one
other development that's been happening
to applications over the years
turns out web apps have been growing
very very incredibly very complicated
over time the first web applications
from the past did very simple
rudimentary things I don't know like to
tell you the time or something nothing
too fancy but over time web applications
have started becoming better bigger
quicker more complicated bigger scale
bigger user base bigger everything and
today we have web applications that can
you know find something from the whole
Internet in a matter of milliseconds or
find what cabs are available around you
all over the world in milliseconds these
are incredible feats if you think about
it and they need incredibly complicated
code to be developed and applied and
this complexity becomes harder and
harder to maintain hang on we have nice
modular architecture on the code side of
things isn't that enough to handle the
complexity during development time who
cares about how the application is
deployed right well with the type of
applications we are talking about the
complexity needs to be handled not just
at the coding side of things they also
need to be handled at the runtime or
execution side of things
having a single thing that you'd apply
didn't work any more this way of having
a single application was called the
monolithic application or monolithic
architecture mono means single lytic
means stone the single stone monolithic
this is the smush basically
what are some of the disadvantages of
this monolithic model first the bigger
the deployment the more challenging the
deployment let me give you an example
let's say you want to push a new feature
to your big monolithic application
alright so among all the code comets
that you want to apply is the single
code comment by this new guy the company
has just hired me not so sure about him
he probably doesn't know much and he's
still learning but his first code commit
ever is just sitting there and you're
worried what do you do well you need to
test the whole thing before you deploy
the whole application you never know
which part of the application that
commit might have broken well I'm
exaggerating here of course but the fact
remains since everything since the whole
application is being deployed every time
you need to test the whole application
every time you'd apply because anything
in it could have a bug introduced and
yeah you have automated tests and all
that jazz but it has a problem second
problem with monolithic architectures
scalability here is an example online
e-commerce sites they have very
unpredictable traffic spikes right so
let's say there is a sale on some
product people rush to the site like
crazy and after the sale is over the
traffic slows down similarly during
holidays there is a spike and there is a
dip thankfully these days we have
elastic servers so when the traffic
spikes up the number of application
server instances are increased but then
when the traffic goes back to normal the
extra servers are retired that's great
but imagine an entire ecommerce website
deployed as a single monolith this
monolith has shopping functionality user
profile the returns functionality a
whole lot of other stuff let's say
there's a traffic spike on the Shopping
pages when the server scale up notice
that all the other functionalities
should scale up as well even though
nobody's using them they have to scale
up because the whole thing is just one
single application so a big ecommerce
site has to be a lot more money to
create these duplicate instances of the
whole application then only a small
portion of the app actually needs to be
scaled up during the time of those
spikes there are a few other challenges
but I won't go into all of them now
let's go back to the story - that one
guy who said hmm there must be a better
way so the idea is like this back when
we were deploying to desktop machines we
had to install the whole app on a single
machine we didn't have a choice but wait
now we have web applications the
applications actually decide on a server
the user was sitting at home on their
computer or phone they don't care where
your application is or have you deployed
or have you executed
they just need one main entry point
application to talk to and from there on
you can run a single application on one
machine or ten applications on ten
machines nobody cares
so here's an idea rather than have the
whole application smushed into one
monolith and deployed into one machine
why not split the application into
smaller mini applications then you can
deploy these mini applications on
different machines you can have them
talk to each other over the network and
together work as the bigger application
take for example the e-commerce site you
could create a shopping catalogue
application that just has the shopping
catalog functionality and you deployed
on a separate server your order
processing done another server use a
profile application on another server
and let's say when the user wants to see
the shopping catalog the view
application which is another application
makes a REST API call to the catalog
applications API and say hey give me the
list of products to show and the API
returns the list and then the view
application returns an HTML for that
list so these many applications talk to
each other over the network by calling
each other's REST API to get whatever
they want from each other okay well how
would this help first the risk of
deployment is eased making a change to
the shopping catalog application well
it's a separate application you can test
and apply just that you don't have to
test and apply the rest of the
application secondly scaling no problem
during the holidays you scale up only
the shopping catalog application you'll
be creating more seven senses only for
the many applications that you need
so these mini applications our services
are what are technically called micro
services micro services are a way of
breaking your application or service
down into standalone independent
applications that can be run on
different hardware or server instances
they all talk to each other over a REST
API and work together to provide the
functionality of your application or
product so all that finds the
organization that you've been making to
the code during development time well
you can have fancy organized separation
of concerns for your applications in
their deployed state as well so you no
longer have one application to build and
apply you have several individual
applications that I'll do like a small
thing each but they work together work
with each other at runtime to form your
actual complete application as far as
your users are concerned now what are
the advantages of micro services we've
covered this you have flexibility
different teams can create and apply
micro services independently they can
put them on different servers or even
build them in different languages or
platforms these micro services talk to
each other through rest so it really
doesn't matter what language you
actually use you no longer have to use a
common language or platform what else
they can be scaled separately during the
shopping traffic spikes just scale
whatever micro services are most used
the other micro services are unaffected
there are many more advantages of course
but you also have to realize this opens
up a whole lot of questions for all the
advantages that that micro services have
they also have some problems as well
earlier you were dealing with one
application now if you're dealing with
tens or maybe hundreds of mini
applications in the form of micro
services so you need to make sure you're
not making things worse in general okay
so you're separating application into
micro services what does this separation
look like how do you ideally split your
application up into micro services so
for example for every feature you need
to add to your application if you need
to make changes to ten different micro
services it kind of defeats the purpose
so you need to separate these
applications well then there's a problem
of how to make sure your micro services
discover each other on a single machine
on a monolith it's fairly obvious HUF
services call each other
but with microservices how do the
services know which REST API endpoints
to call in which environment do you hard
code these URLs or do you have a process
around service discovery so there are a
whole lot of questions here that needs
to be answered and this in a nutshell is
the whole thing about micro service
architecture answering and solving for
these problems is exactly what micro
service architecture is all about and
it's a signs of its own and it it's even
an art of its own before we wrap up this
video though I should clarify that there
isn't a right or a wrong way to do these
things in fact not all applications need
to be architected as micro services no
matter how buzzworthy the term is right
now there are many applications that
should be built with monolithic
architectures please don't believe that
micro services are somehow better than
one of the tech applications they're
just different and both approaches have
their own pros and cons I hope this
video gave you some ideas about micro
services why they were introduced by
they're so popular and what they're
actually all about thank you for
watching