[Music]
let's start the section by a brief
introduction to restful services also
called restful api s-- if you already
know what rest is all about feel free to
skip this video so earlier at the
beginning of the course I introduced you
to the client-server architecture so
most if not all applications we use
these days
follow this architecture the app itself
is the client or the front-end part
under the hood it needs to talk to a
server or the back-end to get or save
the data this communication happens
using the HTTP protocol the same
protocol that powers our web so on the
server we expose a bunch of services
that are accessible via the HTTP
protocol the client can then directly
call the services by sending HTTP
requests now this is where rest comes
into the picture
rest is short for representational state
transfer and I know it probably doesn't
make any sense to you because it was
introduced by a PhD student as part of
his thesis but the theory aside rest is
basically a convention for building
these HTTP services so we use simple
HTTP protocol principles to provide
support to create read update and delete
data we refer to these operations all
together as crud operations now let's
explore this convention using every
award example let's say we have a
company called bitly for renting out
movies we have a client app where we
manage the list of our customers on the
server we should expose a service and an
endpoint like this so really calm slash
API slash customers so the client can
send HTTP requests to this endpoint to
talk to our service now a few things
about this endpoint you need to know
first of all the address can start with
HTTP or HTTPS that depends on the
application and its requirements if you
want the data to be exchanged on a
secure Channel you would use HTTPS after
that we have the domain of the
application
next we have slash API this is not
compulsory but you see a lot of
companies follow this convention to
expose their restful services they
include the word API somewhere in the
address it can be after the domain or it
can be a subdomain like API that vidlink
aam there is no hard and fast rule after
that we have slash customers which
refers to the collection of customers in
our application in the rest world we
refer to this part as a resource we can
expose our resources such as customers
movies rentals on various endpoints so
this is our endpoint to work with the
customers all the operations around
customers such as creating a customer or
updating a customer would be done by
sending an HTTP request to this endpoint
the type of the HTTP request determines
the kind of the operation so every HTTP
request has what we call a verb or
method that determines its type or
intention here are the standard HTTP
methods we have yet for getting data
post or creating data put for updating
data and delayed for deleting data now
let's explore each of these using our
customers example to get the list of all
customers we should send an HTTP GET
request to this address note the full
name customers here it indicates a list
of customers so when we send an HTTP GET
request to this endpoint our service
should send us something like this so we
have an array of customer objects if you
want a single customer we should include
the idea of that customer in the address
then our server would respond with a
customer object like this now to update
a customer we should send an HTTP put
request to this endpoint and note that
again here we're specifying the idea of
the customer to be updated but also we
should include the customer object in
the body of the request so this is a
complete representation of the customer
object with updated properties
we send this to the server and the
server updates the customer with the
given ID according to these values
similarly to delete a customer we should
send an HTTP delete request to this
endpoint but here we don't need to
include the customer object in the body
of the request because all we need to
delete a customer is an ID and finally
to create a customer we need to send an
HTTP POST request to this endpoint note
that here because we are adding a new
customer you're not dealing with a
specific customer so we don't have the
ID in the address you're working with
the collection of customers so we are
posting a new customer to this collector
and that's why we should include the
customer object in the body of the
request the server gets this object and
creates the customer flask so this is
the restful convention we expose our
resources such as customers using a
simple meaningful address and support
various operations around them such as
creating or updating them using standard
HTTP methods hi guys it's March here
thank you for watching my tutorial I
just wanted to let you know that this
video is part of my upcoming node course
where you will learn everything about
node from their basic to the advanced
topics if you want to get the full
course with up to 90% discount click on
the link in the video description and
join my mailing list I'm not gonna spam
you and you can unsubscribe at any time
as soon as I publish the course I'm
gonna send you a coupon so you get the
full course with a huge discount thank
you and have a great day